2.3 Organizational Systems.
Projects operate within the
constraints imposed by the
organization through their
structure and governance framework.
To operate effectively and efficiently,
the project manager needs to understand
where responsibility, accountability and
authority reside within the organization.
This understanding will help the project
manager effectively use his or her power,
influence, competence,
leadership and political
capabilities to successfully
complete the project.
The interaction of multiple factors within
an individual organisation creates a
unique system that impacts the project
operating in that system.
The resulting organisational system
determines the power, influence,
interests, competence
and political capabilities of
the people who are able
to act within the system.
The system factors,
management elements, governance
frameworks and
organisational structure types.
That's from the PIMBOC Guide, page 42.
The first question that we need to answer
is, what is the system?
The Oxford Dictionary defines a system as
a set of things working together as parts
of a mechanism or an interconnecting
network, a complex whole.
The PIMBock defines a system as a
collection of various.
various components that
together can produce results
not obtainable by the
individual components alone.
The principles related to systems are
systems are dynamic.
Systems can be optimized.
System components can be optimized.
Systems and their components
cannot be optimized at the
same time and systems are
non-linear in responsiveness, i.e.
a change in the input does not produce a
predictable change in the output.
The system's dynamics are defined by the
interaction between the components based
on the relationships and dependencies that
exist between the components.
Typically an organization's management is
responsible for its systems.
They examine the optimum trade-offs
between the components and the system in
order to take the appropriate
action in modifying the
systems to achieve the best
outcomes for the organization.
These systems impact the organization's
projects and so the project manager must
consider these systems as well as the
organization's governance framework when
determining how to fulfill the project's
objectives.
Organizational governance frameworks.
Recent PMI research reveals that
governance refers to organizational or
structural arrangements at all levels of
an organization.
designed to determine and influence the
behaviour of the organisation's members.
This research suggests that the concept of
governance is multidimensional and
includes consideration of people,
roles, structures and policies and
requires providing direction and oversight
through data and feedback.
That's from PINBULK guide, page 43.
What is governance?
It's a framework within which an
organisation exercises its authority and
includes rules, policies, procedures,
norms, relationships, systems and processes.
This framework influences how objectives
of the organisation are set and achieved,
risk is monitored and assessed and
performance is optimised.
Two, governance of portfolios,
programs and projects.
As a member of PMI you can download a copy
of many publications free of charge.
For this section you will find the
following publication of value.
It's the governance or portfolio programs
and projects, a practice guide.
This practice guide describes four
governance domains of alignment,
risk, performance and communications.
You can read more about it on the PIMBOC
guide page 44.
Number three, management elements.
These are the key functions or principles
of general management in the organisation
and are allocated within the organisation
according to its governance structure and
the organisational structure types
selected.
They include division of work using
specialised skills and availability to
perform work, authority given to perform
work, responsibility to perform work
appropriately assigned based on such
action.
attributes of skill and experience.
Discipline of action, e.g.
respect for authority, people and rules.
Unity of command, e.g.,
only one person gives
orders for any action or
activity to an individual.
The unity of direction, e.g.
one plan and one head for a group of
activities with the same objective.
General goals of the organization take
precedence over individuals.
goals.
They are to be paid fairly for work
performed, optimal use of resources,
clear communications channels,
write materials to the right person for
the right job at the right time,
fair and equal treatment of people in the
workplace, clear security of work
positions, safety of people in the
workplace, open
contribution to planning and
execution by each
person, and optimal morale.
The PIMBOC guide says in page 45,
performance of these management elements
are assigned to selected individuals
within the organisation.
These individuals might perform the noted
functions within various
organisational structures.
For example, in a
hierarchical structure, there are
horizontal and vertical
levels within the organisation.
These hierarchical levels
range from the line management
level through to the
executive management level.
The responsibility, accountability and
authority assigned to the hierarchical
level indicate how the
individual may perform the
noted function within that
organisational structure.
Number four, organisational structure
types.
Please read the list of
factors in organisation structure
selection and study table 2,
1, on PIMBOC guide page 47.
It compares several
types of organizational
structures and their
influence and projects.
There is no one-size-fits-all structure
for any organisation.
The final structure for
a given organisation is
unique due to the numerous
variables to be considered.
3.
Project Management Office Pinball Guide
defines a project management office as an
organisational structure that standardises
the project related governance processes
and facilitates the sharing of resources,
methodologies, tools and techniques.
The responsibilities of a PMO can range
from providing project management support
functions to the direct management of one
or more projects.
There are several types of PMO in
organisations.
Each type varies in the degree of control
and influence.
It has some projects within the
organisation, such as supportive.
Supportive PMOs provide a consultative
role to projects, by supplying templates,
best practices, training,
access to information
and lessons learned from other projects.
This type of PMO serves as a project
repository.
The degree of control provided by this
type of PMO is low.
And now we move on to controlling PMO.
It provides support and requires
compliance through various means.
The degree of control provided by the PMO
is moderate.
Compliance involve adoption of project
management frameworks and methodologies,
use of specific templates, forms and
tools.
And by that they, I mean they actually
mandate the use of
those templates and tools.
Conformance to governance frameworks.
Then we come to directive PMOs.
They take control of projects by directly
managing the projects.
Project managers are assigned by and
report to the PMO.
The degree of control provided by the PMO
is high.
The project management office may have
organizational wide responsibilities.
It may play a role in supporting strategic
alignment and delivering
organizational value.
The PMO integrates data and information
from organizational strategic projects and
evaluates how higher level strategic
projects are being fulfilled.
The PMO is the natural liaison between the
project's portfolios, programs,
projects and the organisational measuring
systems, e.g.
Balance Scorecard.
The PMO may manage programs of related
projects or portfolios of unrelated
projects and work, but always
with the view to providing
efficiencies and benefits
of a common administration.
A PMO may have the authority to act as an
integral stakeholder and is a key
decision-maker throughout
the life of each project in
order to keep it aligned
with the business objectives.
The PMO may make recommendations,
lead knowledge transfer, terminate
projects and take other actions as
required.
A primary function of a PMO is to support
project managers in a variety of ways,
which may include managing shared
resources across all projects administered
by the PMO, identifying and developing
project management methodology,
best practices and standards, coaching,
mentoring, training and oversight,
monitoring with project management
standards, policies, procedures and
templates by means of project audits,
developing and managing project policies,
procedures, templates and
other shared documentation,
organizational process assets
and coordinating communication and
coordinating communication
across projects.
That brings us to the end of
organizational systems and also to the end
of the environments in which projects
operate.
And the next module is 3.0, the role of
the project manager.
Please read the corresponding project,
sorry, please read the corresponding
chapter in the BIMBOC
guide before watching the video
so that you'll know what
you're meant to be doing.